Guide to the Charles L. Abernethy Sr. papers, 1713-1972, bulk 1907-1959 RL.11844
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles L. Abernethy Sr. papers
1713-1972
1907-1959
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11844
85 Linear Feet 160 boxes; 2 oversize folders Approximately 60,855 items
Charles L. Abernethy, Sr. (1872-1955) was a Democratic Congressman representing eastern North Carolina from 1922-1935. His professional papers consist chiefly of correspondence and records from his law practice and legal cases, with smaller amounts of writings and speeches, financial papers, printed materials, diaries, and some personal papers, including early deeds. There is also a large group of photographs, photo albums, and clippings scrapbooks chiefly documenting Abernethy's political career. One album from 1907 contains postcards of Beaufort, N.C.; another contains photographs of a three-month Congressional trip to Alaska, 1923, and includes images of President and Mrs. Harding and a diary transcript of the trip. Other items include some papers of his son, Charles Laban Abernethy, Jr., also a lawyer, and a volume of his poetry.
Arrangement
Arranged in the following five series: Correspondence; Writings and Speeches; Law Practice and Legal Papers; Financial; Printed Materials and Other Papers; and Photographs, Albums, and Scrapbooks.
Biographical Note
Charles Laban Abernethy, Sr., was born in Burke County, North Carolina in 1872. Educated at UNC-Chapel Hill, he practiced law in Beaufort and New Bern, N.C., then was elected as a Democratic U.S. Congressman representing eastern N.C., serving from 1922 to 1935. He became known especially for his efforts to establish the Intracoastal Waterway in N.C. Charles Laban Abernethy, Jr., his son (1899-1968), was also a lawyer. In the early 20th century, the family resided in Beaufort, then moved to New Bern around 1913. The senior Abernethy suffered from mental illness late in life, and was committed to state institutions. His son became his legal guardian until the elder's death in 1955.
[Sources: Wikipedia, NCPedia, accessed May 2020]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Charles L. Abernethy Sr. papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1970 and 1983.
Scope and Contents
The collection principally comprises a large series of correspondence and legal records accumulated by North Carolina lawyer and politician Charles L. Abernethy, Sr. during his tenure as U.S. Congressman. There are papers relating to the senior Abernethy's law practice and business dealings in Beaufort and New Bern, N.C. (including legal papers concerning land development in Carteret County, Cape Lookout, and Horse Island maintained by both father and son).
Other materials include deeds and other early papers, political speeches, newspaper clippings and scrapbooks of Abernethy's political career, a diary, and the Abernethy coat-of-arms. There are also papers assembled by Abernethy's son, Charles L. Abernethy, Jr., a lawyer in his father's firm, and a volume of his poetry.
A lare group of photographs and albums includes a photograph album containing snapshots the elder Abernethy took during a congressional trip to Alaska for three months of 1923 (including photographs of President and Mrs. Harding), as well as a typescript of his diary from the trip; and an album containing postcards of Beaufort, N.C, in 1907, featuring a celebration of either the 200th anniversary of the town's founding or the opening of passenger and rail service to the town (or both).
Related Materials
Related collection: Charles Laban Abernethy, Jr. papers, 1842-1970, East Carolina University, J. Y. Joyner Library, Greenville, North Carolina.
Lawyers -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; Legislators -- North Carolina; Legislators -- United States; Politicians -- North Carolina -- Correspondence; Beaufort (N.C.) -- Photographs; Carteret County (N.C.) -- History; Craven County (N.C.) -- History; New Bern (N.C.) -- History; North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; Black-and-white photographs; Diaries; Photograph albums; Postcard albums; Scrapbooks
- Correspondence, 1915-1959 and undated; 98 boxes
  - Papers, various printed materials, unsorted (Box 1)
  - 1915-1916 (Box 2)
  - 1917-1922 (Box 3)
  - 1923 January-February (Box 4)
  - 1923 1918, January-March, not weeded (Box 5)
  - 1918, 1925 (Box 6)
  - 1925-1930's, miscellaneous papers with various dates (Box 7)
  - 1926 (Box 8)
  - 1927, July-August (Box 9)
  - 1927, September-October (Box 10)
  - 1927, 1928 (Box 11)
  - 1920 July-December, weeded, 1928, January (Box 12)
  - 1921 January-August, weeded (Box 13)
  - 1921-1922 November, weeded (Box 14)
  - 1922 and undated (Box 15)
  - Clippings, weeded (Box 15)
  - Financial (Box 15)
  - Printed materials (Box 15)
  - Voter lists (Box 15)
  - 1915 and 1917 April-December, not weeded (Box 16)
  - 1924, 1927 January-March, weeded, 1927 Jan-March (Box 17)
  - 1927 (Box 18)
  - 1927 November-December (Box 19)
  - 1927 December 15-31, 1928 February (Box 20)
  - 1928 March (Box 21)
  - 1928 April-May, April-May (Box 22)
  - 1928 June-July (Box 23)
  - 1928 August-October 16 (Box 24)
  - 1928 October 17-November (Box 25)
  - 1928 December-1929 January (Box 26)
  - 1929 February-March (Box 27)
  - 1929 April-May (Box 28)
  - 1929 June, July (Box 29)
  - 1929 August-September 30 (Box 30)
  - 1929 September-October 20 (Box 31)
  - 1929 October 21-November (Box 32)
  - 1929 December and undated (Box 33)
  - 1930 January (Box 34)
  - 1930 February (Box 35)
  - 1930 March-April (Box 36)
  - 1930 April-May (Box 37)
  - 1930 June-July (Box 38)
  - 1930 August-October 20 (Box 39)
  - 1930 October 21-November (Box 40)
  - 1930 December-1931 January 15 (Box 41)
  - 1931 January-March 10 (Box 42)
  - 1931 March 11-31 (Box 43)
  - 1931 April (Box 44)
  - 1931 May (Box 45)
  - 1931 June (Box 46)
  - 1931 October-November (Box 47)
  - 1931 December (Box 48)
  - 1931 July (Box 49)
  - 1931 August-September 15 (Box 50)
  - 1931 September 16-October 15 (Box 52)
  - 1932 January 1-19 (Box 53)
  - 1932 January 20-31 (Box 54)
  - 1932 February 1-14 (Box 55)
  - 1932 February 15-24 (Box 56)
  - 1932 February 25-March 9 (Box 57)
  - 1932 March 10-22 (Box 58)
  - 1932 March 23-April 5 (Box 59)
  - 1932 April 6-22 (Box 60)
  - 1932 April 23-May 15 (Box 61)
  - 1932 May 16-31 (Box 62)
  - 1932 June (Box 63)
  - 1932 July (Box 64)
  - 1932 August (Box 65)
  - 1932 September (Box 66)
  - 1932 October (Box 67)
  - 1932 November (Box 68)
  - 1932 December 1-12 (Box 69)
  - 1932 December 13-1933 January 7 (Box 70)
  - 1933 January 8-17 (Box 71)
  - 1933 January 18- February 10 (Box 72)
  - 1933 February 11-28 (Box 73)
  - 1933 March 1-20 (Box 74)
  - 1933 March 21- April 10 (Box 75)
  - 1933 April 11-May (Box 76)
  - 1933 June-July (Box 77)
  - 1933 August-September 10 (Box 78)
  - 1933 September 11-30 (Box 79)
  - 1933 October (Box 80)
  - 1933 November (Box 81)
  - 1933 December (Box 82)
  - 1934 January 1-24 (Box 83)
  - 1934 January 25-February (Box 84)
  - 1934 February-March 5 (Box 85)
  - 1934 March 6-31 (Box 86)
  - 1934 April (Box 87)
  - 1934 May 1-17 (Box 88)
  - 1934 May 18-June (Box 89)
  - 1934 July-August (Box 90)
  - 1934 September-November (Box 91)
  - 1934 December-1935 (Box 92)
  - 1936 (Box 93)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 94)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 95)
  - 1950-1956 (Box 96)
  - 1957-1959 and other papers (Box 97)
  - Correspondence and other papers: Cape Lookout Land Company (Box 98)
- Writings and Speeches, circa 1920s-1930s; 3 boxes
  - Addresses and writings (Box 99)
  - Addresses and writings (Box 100)
  - Addresses and writings (Box 101)
- Law Practice and Legal Papers, 1915-1935 and undated; 34 boxes
  - Law practice: Sloan affairs, Blackburn estate, Van Kemper vs. Latham, Trustee (Box 102)
  - Law practice, some Sloan affairs (Box 103)
  - Legal matters (Box 104)
  - Legal matters (Box 105)
  - Ye Olde Colony Inn legal matters (Box 106)
  - Ye Olde Colony Inn legal matters, personal legal ­ Abernethy vs. Carter, 1915 (Box 107)
  - Sloan affairs (Box 108)
  - Earl S. Sloan affairs, 1918-1934 (Box 109)
  - Sloan Affairs, legal papers (Box 110)
  - Sloan affairs, Named folders A-B, 1930-1933 (Box 111)
  - Named folders B-C (Box 112)
  - Named folders C-E (Box 113)
  - Named folders E-H (Box 114)
  - Named folders H (Box 115)
  - Named folders H (Box 116)
  - Law practice (Box 117)
  - Law practice (Box 118)
  - Law practice (Box 119)
  - Law practice (Box 120)
  - Law practice (Box 121)
  - Law practice (Box 122)
  - Law practice and legal matters (Box 123)
  - Law practice - Wright estate and undated print materials, 1929-1935 (Box 124)
  - Law practice (Box 125)
  - Law practice (Box 126)
  - Law practice (Box 127)
  - Law practice - Hackburn estate, Van Kemper vs. Latham, Trustee (Box 128)
  - Law practice (Box 129)
  - Law practice (Box 130)
  - Law practice (Box 131)
  - Law practice (Box 132)
  - Law practice - Kentucky-Cumberland Oil Company (Box 133)
  - Law Practice, legal practice; Bennett vs. Bennett, Bennett vs. Swell. Bennett vs. Western Union Telegraph (Box 134)
  - Law practice (Box 135)
- Financial, circa 1910s-1950s; 5 boxes
  - Financial papers (Box 136)
  - Financial papers (Box 137)
  - Financial papers (Box 138)
  - Financial papers (Box 139)
  - Financial papers (Box 142)
- Printed Materials and Other Papers, 1713-1972; 11 boxes
  - School papers, printed matter, invitations and calling cards, and other items (Box 140)
  - Law practice, political (Box 141)
  - Political campaign (1 volume), 1952 (Box 143)
  - Clippings (Box 144)
  - Clippings (Box 145)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 146)
  - Miscellaneous, personal insurance (Box 147)
  - Printed materials (Box 148)
  - Clippings of Abernethy vs. Carter, 1915 (Box 149)
  - Miscellaneous, deeds (Box 150)
  - Miscellaneous, personal, biographical, clippings, printed material, 1920s (Box 151)
  - Oversize papers (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Oversize papers (Oversize-folder 2)
- Photographs, Albums, and Scrapbooks, circa 1907-1940s; 9 boxes
  - Scrapbooks (Box 152)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 153)
  - Photograph albums, including Alaska trip and Beaufort albums, circa 1907-1923 (Box 154)
  - Photographs: Family (Box 155)
  - Photographs: Alaska trip, 1923; Panama, Rocky Mountains (Box 156)
  - Family papers, miscellaneous (Box 157)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 158)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 159)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 160)